Guide to the Felix Adler Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Felix Adler Papers
1830-1933.
Adler, Felix, 1851-1933.
27 linear ft. (ca. 25,000 items in 86 boxes and 1 oversize folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078424
Felix Adler, religious leader and educator, taught courses in social and political ethics at Columbia between 1902 and 1933. The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, notes, photographs, and printed materials.
History
Felix Adler (Columbia A.B., 1870), religious leader and educator, taught courses in social and political ethics at Columbia between 1902 and 1933.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, notes, photographs, and printed materials. Included are letters from the leaders and members of the Society for Ethical Culture which Adler founded in 1976; the ethical movement abroad; religious and political figures; and extensive correspondence with his family, particularly his wife, Helen Goldmark Adler, to whom Adler wrote long, detailed letters about his activities. The family letters date back to his parents' generation when they were still living in Germany and many are in German and Hebrew. Among the correspondents are Louis D. Brandeis, John Dewey, Abraham Geiger, Charles Evans Hughes, William James, Jacob Riis, and Lillian Wald. There is a series of typescript copies of letters to and from Adler which were probably prepared for Adler's wife and daughter Eleanor as working copies for a projected life and letters of Adler. Both have made annotations on the copies, The manuscripts and typescripts span Adler's life. Included are childhood and school days poems and essays, and later manuscripts for published and unpublished lectures, articles, essays, books, notes, diaries, and random jottings on a wide range of topics: ethics, morality, philosophy, theology, Bible, Judaism, politics, social reform, arts and letters. There is a full set of lecture notes for his courses at Columbia University. In addition to his voluminous diary entires, he also kept records of conversations with individuals he met over the years.
Also included are records for the Society for Ethical Culture and its schools.
There is an incomplete index of personal names for Classification 100 and 200 only.
Arrangement
Selected items cataloged; much of the collection is classified by subject and arranged in numbered folders. The collection is divided into two series:
Series I. Unclassified Papers
Subseries I.1. Cataloged Correspondence
Subseries I.2. Arranged Correspondence
Subseries I.3. Arranged Manuscripts and Documents
Subseries I.4. Printed Material and Scrapbooks
Series II. Classified Papers
Subseries II.1. Columbia Lectures (100)
Subseries II.2. General Classification (200) and Index of Names to Series II.2 (200)
Subseries II.3. Single Lectures and Addresses by Dr. Adler (500)
Subseries II.4. Lecture Series by Dr. Adler; Berlin Lectures; Miscellaneous Manuscripts (600)
Subjects
Society for Ethical Culture.; Adler, Helen Goldmark.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Geiger, Abraham, 1810-1874.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; James, William, 1842-1910.; Riis, Jacob A. (Jacob August), 1849-1914.; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940.; Religion.; Philosophy and religion.; Ethics.; Diaries; Photoprints
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 6-86. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions
Acquisition
1974 Papers Friess, Mr. and Mrs. Horace L. Gift
1977 Papers Gutmann, Ruth Adler Friess Gift
Alternate Formats
Josephine Shaw letters are on microfilm.
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Horace L. Friess, 1974 and Mrs. Ruth Adler Freiss Gutmann, 1976-78 and 1981.
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Horace L. Friess Papers, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Algernon D. Black Papers, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Finding aid in repository and online.
- Series I: Unclassified Papers
  - Subseries I.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Abbot, Francis Ellingwood (Box 1)
    - Abbott, Lyman (Box 1)
    - Addams, Jane (Box 1)
    - Adler, Felix
      - Arranged by recipient: to Eleanor Adler - to Helen Goldmark Adler, 1905 (Box 1)
      - Arranged by recipient: to Helen Goldmark Adler, 1905 - 1931 - to George O'Dell (Box 2)
      - Arranged by recipient: to his Parents - to Henry J. Wolf (Box 3)
      - p.d., 1p. (Box 3)
        (invitation to opening ceremonies for BrooklYn Bridge)
    - Adler, Samuel (Box 3)
    - Alexander, John White (Box 3)
    - Arnold, Matthew (Box 3)
    - Baldwin, William Henry, Jr. (Box 3)
    - Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter (Box 3)
    - Baumgarten, Otto (Box 3)
    - Bernstorff, Johann Heinrich, Count von (Box 3)
    - Bessels, Emil (Box 3)
    - Black, Algernon D. (Box 3)
    - Blackwell, Emily (Box 3)
    - Boas, Franz (Box 3)
    - Boerrer, Wilhelm (Box 3)
    - Brace, Charles Loring (Box 3)
    - Brandeis, Alice (Mrs. Louis D.) (Box 4)
    - Brandeis, Louis Dembitz (Box 4)
    - Brickell, Herschel (Box 4)
    - Brown, William Adams (Box 4)
    - Burgess, John William (Box 4)
    - Burr, George Lincoln (Box 4)
    - Bush, Wendell T. (Box 4)
    - Butler, Nicholas Murray (Box 4)
    - Cardozo, Benjamin Nathan (Box 4)
    - Carpenter, Joseph Estlin (Box 4)
    - Sheyne, Thomas Kelly (Box 4)
    - Chubb, Percival (Box 4)
    - Claretie, Jules (Box 4)
    - Clarke, Frank Wigglesworth (Box 4)
    - Coffin, Henry Sloane (Box 4)
    - Cohen, Morris Raphael (Box 4)
    - Coit, Stanton (Box 4)
    - Conway, Moncure Daniel (Box 4)
    - Coss, John J. (Box 4)
    - Cronbach, Abraham (Box 4)
    - Crothers, Samuel M. (Box 4)
    - Davis, William Morris (Box 4)
    - Deland, Margaret (Box 4)
    - Dewey, John (Box 4)
    - Dole, Charles F. (Box 4)
    - Drummond, William Hamilton (Box 4)
    - Eckstein, Walther (Box 4)
    - Eliot, Charles William (Box 4)
    - Elliott, John Lovejoy (Box 4)
    - Ewald, Oscar (Box 4)
    - Felsenthal, Bernhard (Box 4)
    - Foerster, Friedrich Wilhelm (Box 4)
    - Frothingham, Octavius Brooks (Box 4)
    - Gannett, Mary Thorn Lewis (Mrs. William Channing) (Box 4)
    - Geiger, Abraham (Box 4)
    - Gizycke, George von (Box 4)
    - Godber, William Samuel (Box 4)
    - Goldmark, Henry (Box 4)
    - Groszmann, Maximilian Paul Eugen (Box 4)
    - Guthrie, William Norman (Box 4)
    - Haeckel, Ernst Heinrich (Box 4)
    - Harrison, Frederic (Box 4)
    - Hellman, Frances (Box 4)
    - Hewitt, Abram Stevens (Box 4)
    - Hill, David Jaynes (Box 4)
    - Hobson, John Atkinson (Box 4)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (Box 4)
    - Holt, Winifred (Box 4)
    - Holyoake, George Jacob (Box 4)
    - Hughes, Charles Evans (Box 4)
    - Hughes, Thomas (Box 4)
    - Jacks, Lawrence Pearsall (Box 4)
    - Jackson, Abraham Valentine Williams (Box 4)
    - James, William (Box 4)
    - Janschul, Catherine (Mrs. Ivan) (Box 4)
    - Jewett, Rutger Bleecker (Box 4)
    - Kelley, Edgar Stillman (Box 4)
    - Kellogg, Paul Underwood (Box 4)
    - Keppel, Frederick Paul (Box 4)
    - Keyser, Cassius Jackson (Box 4)
    - Kindler, Hans (Box 4)
    - Kohn, Robert David (Box 4)
    - Lang, John Dunmore (Box 4)
    - Low, Seth (Box 4)
    - Lowell, Josephine Shaw (Box 4)
      (Also available on microfilm )
    - Mackenzie, John Stuart (Box 4)
    - Marshall, Henry Rutgers (Box 4)
    - Martineau, James (Box 4)
    - Mead, Edwin Doak (Box 4)
    - Mendes, Henry Pereira (Box 4)
    - Metzger, Moïse (Box 4)
    - Miller, Dickinson Sergeant (Box 4)
    - Montefiore, Claude Joseph Goldsmid (Box 4)
    - Muzzey, David Saville (Box 4)
    - Newton, Richard Heber (Box 4)
    - O'Dell, George Edward (Box 5)
    - Otto, Max Carl (Box 5)
    - Palmer, GeDl1ge Herbert (Box 5)
    - Paszkowski, Wilhelm (Box 5)
    - Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer (Box 5)
    - Peabody, George Foster (Box 5)
    - Pollock, Frederick, 3rd baronet (Box 5)
    - Ponsonby, 1st Baron, of Shulbrede (Box 5)
    - Potter, Henry Codman (Box 5)
    - Pound, Roscoe Puig Casauraunc, José Manuel (Box 5)
    - Riis, Jacob August (Box 5)
    - Rockefeller, John Davison, 1874-1950 (Box 5)
    - Rogers, Henry Huddleston (Box 5)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box 5)
    - Royce, Josiah (Box 5)
    - Salter, William Mackintire (Box 5)
    - Sayce, Archibald Henry (Box 5)
    - Schiff, Jacob Henry (Box 5)
    - Schmoller, Gustav von (Box 5)
    - Sedgwick, Ellery (Box 5)
    - Seligman, Edwin Robert Anderson (Box 5)
    - Seligman, Isaac Newton (Box 5)
    - Seligman, Joseph (Box 5)
    - Sheean, Vincent (Box 5)
    - Sheldon, Walter L. (Box 5)
    - Shepard, Edward Martin (Box 5)
    - Smalley, Eugene Via:"gil (Box 5)
    - Smith, Arthur Lionel (Box 5)
    - Snell, Henry, Baron Snell (Box 5)
    - Steinschneider, Moritz (Box 5)
    - Stone, William (Box 5)
    - Strunsky, Manya Gordon (Mrs. Simeon) (Box 5)
    - Tawney, Richard Henry (Box 5)
    - Thayer, Abbott H. (Box 5)
    - Tonnies, Ferdinand (Box 5)
    - Troup, Emily Josephine (Box 5)
    - Trübner, Nicholas (Box 5)
    - Tylor, Edward Burnett (Box 5)
    - Vaihinger, Hans (Box 5)
    - Villard, Oswald Garrison (Box 5)
    - Wald, Lillian D. (Box 5)
    - Wells, Kate Gannett (Box 5)
    - Weston, Samuel Burns (Box 5)
    - Weyl, Walker E. (Box 5)
    - Whipple, Edwin Percy (Box 5)
    - White, Andrew Dickson (Box 5)
    - Whitman, Chares Seymour (Box 5)
    - Whitman, Walt (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Woodrow (Box 5)
    - Wise, Louise Waterman (Mrs. Stephen Samuel) (Box 5)
    - Wolf, Henry J. (Box 5)
    - Zarncke, Friedrremh (Box 5)
  - Subseries I.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Adler, Felix
      - Typed copies of his letters, 1870-1933 (Box 6)
      - Typed copies of letters received by him, 1868-1933 (Box 7)
      - Envelopes received by him (without letters) (Box 7)
    - A (Box 8)
    - Adler, Abraham (Box 8)
    - Adler, Babette (Mrs. Nathan?) (Box 8)
    - Adler, Charles (Box 8)
    - Adler, Eleanor H. (Box 8)
    - Adler, Felix
      - Envelopes addressed by him (Box 8)
      - Letters Received by him
        - A-W (Box 8)
        - Unidentified (Box 8)
        - 80th Birthday, 1931 (Box 8)
    - Adler, Frieda Grumhaber (Mrs. Isaac) (Box 8)
    - Adler, Helen Goldmark (Mrs. Felix), 1879 - 1946 (Box 9)
    - Adler, Henrietta (Mras. Samuel) (Box 9)
    - Adler, Isaac (Box 9)
    - Adler, Laurence (Box 9)
    - Adler, Margaret (Box 9)
    - Adler, Rachel (Mrs. Abraham) (Box 9)
    - Adler, Samuel, letters received (Box 9)
    - Adler, Waldo (Box 9)
    - Adler, Willie (Box 9)
    - B-F (Box 9)
    - Friess, Horace L. (Box 9)
    - G (Box 9)
    - Goldman, Sarah Adler (Mrs. Julius) (Box 9)
    - Gutmann, Ruth Adler Friess (Mrs. James) (Box 9)
    - H-K (Box 9)
    - Kirschner, Ellen (Box 9)
    - L-M (Box 9)
    - Maier, Joseph &Alice (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous letters - undientified (Box 9)
    - N-O (Box 9)
    - P-W (Box 9)
    - Walz, Isidor (Box 9)
    - Wendt, Anna (Box 9)
    - Y (Box 9)
  - Subseries I.3: Arranged Documents and Manuscripts
    - Adler, Felix
      - Arranged Documents
        - Miscellaneous bills and receipts (Box 10)
        - Miscellaneous agreements (Box 10)
      - Arranged Manuscripts
        - Biographical notes, obituaries, eulogies (Box 10)
        - Memorabilia (Box 10)
    - Society for An Ethical Culture
      - American Ethical Union Convention, 1907 May 9-12 (Box 11)
      - Annual meeting, 1929 November 11 (Box 11)
      - Annual report, 1903 May 11 (Box 11)
      - Carnegie Hall (Box 11)
      - Chorus (Box 11)
      - Clubs and other groups (Box 11)
      - Constitution and by-laws (Box 11)
      - Convention--Chicago--Delegates, 1895 (Box 11)
      - Corporate purposes--Certificate for extension (Box 11)
      - Correspondence
        - B-K (Box 11)
        - Kohn, Albert M. (Box 11)
        - L-M (Box 11)
        - Lange, J.D. (Box 11)
        - O-P (Box 11)
        - Rosenbaum, Julius (Box 11)
        - S-T (Box 11)
        - V-W (Box 11)
      - Documents, re: Felix Adler (Box 11)
      - Ethical Culture Building--Examination by New York City Board of (Box 11)
      - Transportation, 1925 (Box 11)
      - Ethical Culture School (Box 11)
      - Fieldston School (Box 11)
      - Finance Committee - Meeting Minutes, 1900 January 7 (Box 11)
      - Financial records, miscellaneous, 1886-1929 (Box 11)
      - Hirsch Fund (Box 11)
      - International Union--Constitution (Box 11)
      - Members and membership (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous documents (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous Ethical Societies (Box 11)
      - Mt. Pleasant Cemetery--Report of Committee, 1904 (Box 11)
      - Printed material (printed by SEC) (Box 11)
      - Publication Committee (Box 11)
      - School budgets, 1903-1911 (Box 12)
      - Sunday School Committee (Box 12)
      - Treasurer's reports, 1892 -1910 (Box 12)
      - Trustees
        - Meetings (Box 12)
        - Members (Box 12)
      - Twentieth Anniversary & Tenth Convention, Philadelphia, 1905 May (Box 12)
      - Women's Conference, 1895 August 18 (Box 12)
      - Workingman's Lyceum (Box 12)
      - Young Men's Union (Box 12)
      - Bound volumes:
        - Building Fund, Kindergarten & Workingman's School (Box 12)
        - Record of lectures delivered, 1892-1939 (Box 12)
        - Sunday lectures, Albert A. Levi, Winter of 1876-1877 (Box 12)
        - Register of Visitors and/or delegates to Ethical Culture Society, 1904 November-1921 May (Box 12)
    - Biographical material on Felix Adler: Life and Letters of Felix Adler
      - Biographical material by his family for proposed biography by Eleanor Adler. (Box 13)
      - Rejected manuscripts for the book (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous biographical manuscripts (Box 14)
    - Adler Family
      - Biographical
        - Adler, Helen Goldmark (Mrs. Felix) (Box 15)
        - Adler, Samuel (Box 15)
        - Adler family (Box 15)
      - Documents
        - Adler, Florence (Box 15)
        - Adler, Margaret (Box 15)
        - Adler, Samuel (Box 15)
        - Adler, Waldo (Box 15)
      - Manuscripts
        - Adler, Eleanor (Box 15)
        - Adler, Helen Goldmark (Mrs. Felix) (Box 15)
        - Adler, Isaac, "Zum Geburtstag 1851” (Box 15)
          (poem on the birth of Felix)
        - Adler, Samuel (Box 15)
        - Adler, Waldo (Box 15)
        - Gutmann, Ruth Adler Friess (Mrs. James) (Box 15)
      - Photographs
        - Adler family (Box 15)
    - Adler, Laurence
      - Manuscripts (Box 16)
      - Memoirs - Musical and Otherwise (Box 16)
        (t.ms., draft)
      - Memoirs - Musical and Otherwise (Box 16)
        (t.ms)
      - Memorabilia--Japan (Box 16)
      - Music--Compositions, Programs, Reviews (Box 16)
      - Photographs
        - Traveling (Box 16)
        - Memoirs - Musical and Otherwise (Box 16)
      - Printed material
        - magazine (Box 16)
        - Memoirs - Musical and Otherwise (Box 16)
  - Subseries I.4: Printed Material and Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1880-90 (clippings: tenement-house reforms, speeches, SEC) (Box 17)
      - 1884 (Box 17)
        (clippings: tenement-house reforms)
      - 1908-1909 (Box 17)
        (clippings, memorabilia: Berlin professorship)
      - 1909-1911 (Box 17)
        (clippings, memorabilia: Berlin professorship, London Races Congress)
      - 1878-80 (Box 18)
        (clippings, memorabilia: re Adler, SEC)
      - 1882-84 (Box 18)
        (clippings: SEC, "creed," United Relief work, et al)
      - 1880-1933 (Box 18)
        (clippings (mainly re: wedding); photos (biog.)
      - 1890 (Box 18)
        (memorabilia: People's free Sunday concerts)
    - Printed Material
      (Books, lectures, magazine articles, etc., by Felix Adler)
      - Address at meeting to organize the Society for Ethical, 1876 May 15 (Box 19)
      - Aims of the Ethical Movement, 1919 November 29 (Box 19)
      - Armistice Anniversary address--New York, Soc. for Ethical Culture, 1931 November 8 (Box 19)
      - American ideals contrasted with German and English, circa 1916 (Box 19)
        (German translation, 1931 May 31)
      - The binders of life and man's spiritual liberation, 1927 November 20 (Box 19)
      - Can we afford to rule subject peoples? SEC address, 1900 March 18 (Box 19)
      - Child labor and its evils (Carnegie Hall), 1905 January 29 (Box 19)
      - Dedication of Ethical Society meeting-house in New York to its civic uses, 1910 December (Box 19)
      - The democratic ideal in education (Century Magazine), 1889 October (Box 19)
      - Disarmament: its ideals and possibilities (NY SEC), 1921 November 6 (Box 19)
      - The essentials of ethical religion (NY SEC), 1929 March 31 (Box 19)
      - The ethical ideal on Fieldston Hill (Laying of cornerstone), 1927 October 15 (Box 19)
      - The ethical problem (American Philosophical Ass'n., Phila.), 1928 December 29 (Box 19)
      - An ethical program for business men (SEC), undated (Box 19)
      - Ethics and culture (Harvard Philosophical Club), 1888 January 9 (Box 19)
      - False ethics in social reform movements, 1913 (Box 19)
      - 55th anniversary of founding of Ethical Culture Movement, 1931 May 10 (Box 19)
      - The four types of suffering (Ethical addresses), circa 1885 (Box 19)
      - Goethe's ideal of culture, 1924 January 20 (Box 19)
      - Huxley's attitude toward religion, 1901 January 27 (Box 19)
      - The ideal of culture for business men (American Ethical Union), 1924 March, 1924 (Box 19)
      - Ideals for our new school, 1926 February 5 (Box 19)
      - The influence of the physical geography of Palestine on Hebrew thought (American Geographical Society), Undated (Box 19)
      - The life and death of Socrates, 1903 May 10 (Box 19)
      - The meaning of an Ethical Society -(American Ethical Union), 1923 April (Box 19)
      - The meaning of temperance as an aid to the spiritual life, 1989 January 9 (Box 19)
      - Memorial--O.B. Frothingham, 1985 December (Box 19)
      - Message of Dante, 1910 November 8 (Box 19)
      - The modern saint, Probably 1894 March 11 (Box 19)
      - The Monroe Doctrine and war spirit in the U.S. (SEC), 1896 January 5 (Box 19)
      - The moral instruction of the young (Convention of Ethical Societies, Philadelphia)
        - 1889 January 27 (Box 19)
        - Abstract, in Ethical Record, 1889 July (Box 19)
      - Nationalism and Zionism, 1919 March (Box 19)
        (reprint from The Standard)
      - The need of a new moral movement in religion
        - SEC, 1883 February 11 (Box 19)
        - SEC, Chicago, 1883 February 18 (Box 19)
      - The new attitude toward others, 1902 January 5 (Box 19)
      - The new education in the new America, 1918 January 20 (Box 19)
      - On the exegesis and criticism of the Old Testament (American Oriental Society), 1874 May 20 (Box 19)
      - Permanence or impermanence of marriage (Hibbert Journal), 1923 October (Box 19)
      - Personality - (The Standard), 1925 December (Box 19)
        (Written for the Fourth International Moral Education Congress, Rome, 1926)
      - The Philippine War (SEC), 1902 April (Box 19)
      - The prerequisites of a religion (SEC), circa 1903 (Box 19)
      - A protest against the Russian treaty (SEC), 1893 March 26 (Box 19)
      - The punishment of children (SEC), 1886 February (Box 19)
      - The revival of anti-Semitism (AEU), 1920 December 5 (Box 19)
      - The right of political asylum threatened (AEU), 19009 January (Box 19)
      - The Sabbath and the World's Fair (SEC), 1893 January 29 (Box 19)
      - Self-help in affliction, 1906 January 21 (Box 19)
      - The spiritual meaning of marriage (SEC), circa 1912 (Box 19)
      - The Treaty's moral failure (The Nation), 1919 May 24 (Box 19)
      - Words spoken by Dr. Felix Adler at the bier of Franklin C. Lewis (The Standard), 1930 February 14 (Box 19)
      - Anniversary lecture, 1879 May 11 (Box 19)
        (proof)
      - The recent persecution of the Jews (SEC), 1879 December 28 (Box 19)
      - Nationalism and Zionism (in The Standard), 1919 March (Box 19)
  - Printed Material by other people
    - Felix Adler Lectures, 1939-1950 (Box 20)
    - Helen Adler (Box 20)
    - Foerster, Friedrich Wilhelm--Material about Adler (Box 20)
    - Davidson, J.--Notes on Adler's Ethical Philosophy of Life (Box 20)
    - Printed material by others, not about Adler (Box 20)
    - Adler, Samuel. A Guide to the Instruction in the Israelitish Religion, 1860 (Box 20)
      (Felix Adler’s copy)
    - Lange, Friedrich. Die Arbeiterfrage, 1875 (Box 20)
- Series II: Classified Papers
  The Classification Scheme of the papers is as follows:
  100 Classification with Subdivisions of 100: Lists of Courses Given at Columbia University
  200 Classification with Subdivisions for 200-225: General Classification (Includes Index of Names)
  500 Classification with Subdivisions of 500: Single Lectures and Addresses by Dr. Adler
  600 Classification and Subdivisions of 600: Lecture Series by Dr. Adler; Berlin Lectures and German Material; Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Documents
  - Subseries II.1: Columbia Lectures (100)
    The Classification with Subdivisions of 100, List of Courses Given at Columbia University:
    1903: Ethical Philosophy; Political and Social Ethics; Psychology and Ethics; Ethical Philosophy; Political and Social Ethics
    1903-1904: Moral Instruction
    1904: Social Philosophy: The Ethical Theory of Society; The Present Situation; Moral Education in the High School (See also special papers)
    1905: Personal Ethics; Psychology and Ethics
    1906: Vocational Ethics (See also student notes); Social Ethics (Notes by Mr. Sprague; Notes on Marx)
    1907-7: Moral Education of the Adult
    1907: Political Ethics (Student Notes also by Jackson)
    1907-8: Ethical Philosophy
    1908: Ethical Philosophy (See also student notes); Political Ethics; Social Ethics
    1909-1910: Social Ethics
    1910-1911: Ethical Development Throughout Life, Notes by Tsanoff; The Relation of Ethics to Religion
    1911: Ethical Education Throughout Life; Moral Instruction (Mrs. Adler's notes); Ethical Systems
    1911-1912: Social Reform
    1912: Ethical Systems
    1912-1913: Individual and Social Ethics
    1913: Ethical Philosophy; Social Service
    1913-1914: (Mr. O’Dell’s notes)
    1914: Metaphysical Background of Dr. Adler’s Ethics; Ethical Theory
    1914-1915: Application of Ethical Theory to Life (See also Mr. O’Dell’s notes)
    1915: Social Ethics
    1915-1916: Ethical Philosophy
    1916-1917: (Student notes- Jacobs The Ethics of Aristotle and Kent); Appraisement of Ethics Philosophies; (Student’s papers--Winston, Jacobs, Neff, Wilson)
    1917-1918: Main Problems of Ethics
    1918-1919: Political Ethics
    Undated Social Ethics
    The detailed list of courses in the Container List is followed by a description of the main topics discussed in each course.
    - Psychology and Ethics (Notes by Harold D. Clum), 1903 (Box 21)
      (1903 A. Ethical facts. Judgment. Relation of Psychology to Ethics. Psychology Materialistic, descriptive. Character. Polarities. Jekyl and Hyde. Shelley, Milton, Dickens, Hugo, Fox. Savonarola.
      Ethical Opinion on Institutionalism. Empiricalism. Equality. Moral Obligation. Superstition. Sacerdotal Conscience. Categorical Imperative. The Evolutionists. The Utilitarians. Happiness Theory, Kant. Unconditional Obligation. Absolute Truth. Dr. Adler’s System.)
    - Ethical Philosophy, 1903 February-March (Box 21)